U.S.S. Kelvin, go for Starfleet Base.
Starfleet Base, we've sent you
a transmission. Did you receive?
Kelvin, have you double-checked
those readings?
Our gravitational sensors are
going crazy here. You should see this.
It looks like a lightning storm.
What you've sent us
doesn't seem possible.
Yes, ma'am. I understand.
That's why we sent it.
- Report.
- It's still out of visual range.
- Give me 20 seconds.
- Alert Captain Robau
that Starfleet advises your ship
to proceed with caution.
Polarize the viewscreen.
Could whatever this is
be of Klingon origin?
Captain, we have visual.
- Repeat. Could this be Klingon?
- Negative, Lieutenant.
You're 75,000 kilometers from...
Captain, are you seeing this?
My God.
I have a reading.
- They've locked weapons on us!
- Red alert!
Torpedo locked on us at 320 degrees,
- mark 2.
- Arm weapons!
Evasive pattern Delta-five!
Incoming fast!
Fire all phasers! Damage report.
Warp drive's been knocked out!
Never seen anything like it.
Weapons are off-line. Main power 38%.
- They're firing another!
- All power to forward shields!
Lieutenant!
Atmospheric stabilization has been lost.
- Were our shields even up?
- Oxygen failing, Decks 7 to 13.
- We have confirmed casualties, sir.
- Shields 11% and dropping.
Ten percent. Shields at nine.
We're dropping here.
All remaining power to forward shields.
Prepare shuttles for evacuation.
Hello.
My commander requests
the presence of your Captain
in order to negotiate a cease-fire.
You will come aboard our ship
via shuttlecraft.
Your refusal would be unwise.
Walk with me.
If I don't report in 15 minutes,
evacuate the crew.
- Sir, we could issue...
- There is no help for us out here.
Use autopilot.
- And get off this ship.
- Aye, Captain.
You're Captain now, Mr. Kirk.
His heart rate's elevated.
Look at this ship.
- Are you familiar with this craft?
- Who is your commander?
- Is it him?
- I will speak for Captain Nero.
Then ask Captain Nero what gives him
the right to attack a Federation vessel.
Do you know the location
of Ambassador Spock?
I'm unfamiliar with Ambassador Spock.
- What is the current stardate?
- Stardate?
Twenty-two thirty-three zero-four.
Where are you from?
Sir, they're locked on our signal.
They're launching again!
Bravo-six maneuver! Fire full spread!
- Seventeen more out!
- I'm initiating General Order 13!
- We're evacuating!
- Yes, sir!
All decks, this is the Captain speaking.
Evacuate the ship immediately.
Get to your designated shuttlecraft.
Repeat. Evacuate...
That's George's voice.
What's happening?
You'll deliver in the shuttle. Go!
Move! This one's closed!
Let's go! Get him up!
I'm on my way!
- George.
- You're okay. Thank God.
I have medical shuttle 37 standing by.
Get to it now. Can you do that?
- Yes.
- Everything's gonna be okay.
- Do exactly as I say. Shuttle 37.
- George, it's coming.
- Our baby, it's coming now.
- I'm on my way.
Autopilot function has been destroyed.
Manual operation only.
Clear those decks now!
Get to the shuttles! Move, move, move!
Get to the hangar deck!
Get to the hangar deck! Let's move it!
- That was a big one.
- Just keep breathing. You'll be fine.
- And the baby, too, right?
- And the baby, too.
Right here. Go ahead and sit back.
Captain to shuttle 37.
Is my wife onboard?
- Yes, sir, she is.
- I need you to go now. Do you hear me?
- We're waiting on you, sir.
- No, just go. Take off immediately.
- That's an order.
- Yes, sir.
No, wait! We can't go yet!
Please stop! Stop!
George? The shuttle's leaving.
Where are you?
Sweetheart, listen to me.
I'm not gonna be there.
- No.
- This is the only way you'll survive.
Are you still on the ship?
You have to be here!
The shuttles will never make it
if I don't fight them off.
George, I can't do this without you.
Okay, I need you to push now.
- What is it?
- It's a boy.
A boy?
Tell me about him.
He's beautiful.
George, you should be here.
Impact alert.
- What are we gonna call him?
- We can name him after your father.
"Tiberius"? You kidding me?
No, that's the worst.
Let's name him after your dad.
Let's call him Jim.
Jim. Okay. Jim it is.
- Sweetheart, can you hear me?
- I hear you!
I love you so much. I love you...
Hey, are you out of your mind?
That car is an antique.
You think you can get away with this
just 'cause your mother's off planet?
You get your ass back home now!
You live in my house, buddy.
You live in my house, and that's my car.
You get one scratch on that car,
and I'm gonna whip your...
Yeah!
Hey, Johnny!
Citizen! Pull over.
No!
Is there a problem, Officer?
Citizen, what is your name?
My name is James Tiberius Kirk.
What is the formula
for the volume of a sphere?
Four-thirds pi times the radius cubed.
One-point-two-six.
An ellipse.
What is the electrical charge
of an up-type quark?
Positive two-thirds.
What is the square root of 2,396,324?
- 1,548.
- What is the dimensionality...
Dimensionality equals the logarithm
and divided by...
Non-excludability and non-rivalry...
Four-thirds pi times the radius cubed.
When it is morally praiseworthy
but not morally obligatory.
Spock!
I presume you've prepared
new insults for today.
Affirmative.
This is your thirty-fifth attempt to elicit
an emotional response from me.
You're neither human nor Vulcan, and
therefore have no place in this universe.
Look. He has human eyes.
They look sad, don't they?
Perhaps an emotional response
requires physical stimuli.
He's a traitor, you know. Your father.
For marrying her. That human whore.
They called you a traitor.
Emotions run deep within our race.
In many ways,
more deeply than in humans.
Logic offers a serenity
humans seldom experience.
The control of feelings,
so that they do not control you.
You suggest
that I should be completely Vulcan,
and yet, you married a human.
As ambassador to Earth, it is my duty
to observe
and understand human behavior.
Marrying your mother was
logical.
Spock. You are fully capable
of deciding your own destiny.
The question you face is,
which path will you choose?
This is something only you can decide.
Spock, come here, let me see you.
- No.
- Spock.
There's no need to be anxious.
You'll do fine.
I am hardly anxious, Mother.
And "fine" has variable definitions.
"Fine" is unacceptable.
Okay.
- May I ask a personal query?
- Anything.
Should I choose to complete
the Vulcan discipline of Kolinahr
and purge all emotion,
I trust you will not feel
it reflects judgment upon you.
Spock.
As always, whatever you choose to be,
you will have a proud mother.
You have surpassed the expectations
of your instructors.
Your final record is flawless,
with one exception.
I see that you have applied
to Starfleet as well.
It was logical
to cultivate multiple options.
Logical, but unnecessary.
You are hereby accepted
to the Vulcan Science Academy.
It is truly remarkable, Spock,
that you have achieved so much
despite your disadvantage.
All rise!
If you would clarify, Minister,
- to what disadvantage are you referring?
- Your human mother.
Council. Ministers, I must decline.
No Vulcan has ever declined
admission to this Academy.
Then as I am half human,
your record remains untarnished.
Spock, you have made a commitment
to honor the Vulcan way.
Why did you come
before this council today?
Was it to satisfy
your emotional need to rebel?
The only emotion I wish to convey
is gratitude.
Thank you, Ministers,
for your consideration.
Live long and prosper.
- How are you?
- Hey.
- Hi.
Hi, I'd like a Klabnian Fire Tea,
three Budweiser Classics,
- two Cardassian Sunrises and...
- Gotta try the Slusho. It's good.
The Slusho mix. Thank you.
That's a lot of drinks for one woman.
- And a shot of Jack, straight up.
- Make that two. Her shot's on me.
Her shot's on her. Thanks but no thanks.
Don't you want to at least
know my name
before you completely reject me?
- I'm fine without it.
- You are fine without it.
It's Jim. Jim Kirk.
If you don't tell me your name,
I'm gonna have to make one up.
- It's Uhura.
- Uhura? No way!
That's the name
I was gonna make up for you.
- Uhura what?
- Just Uhura.
They don't have last names
in your world?
Uhura is my last name.
Well, they don't have first names
in your world?
Excuse me, buddy.
So, you're a cadet, you're studying.
What's your focus?
Xenolinguistics.
You have no idea what that means.
The study of alien languages.
Morphology, phonology, syntax.
It means you've got a talented tongue.
I'm impressed.
For a moment there,
I thought you were just a dumb hick
- who only has sex with farm animals.
- Well, not only.
This townie isn't bothering you, right?
Beyond belief.
But it's nothing I can't handle.
You could handle me.
That's an invitation.
- Hey, you better mind your manners.
- Relax, cupcake. It was a joke.
Hey, farm boy. Maybe you can't count,
but there are four of us and one of you.
So get some more guys,
and then it'll be an even fight.
Guys, stop it.
Stop it!
Enough!
Guys, he's had enough!
Outside, all of you.
- Now!
- Yes, sir!
- He wouldn't even listen!
- I just bought a drink.
- Can you believe this?
- It's not really fair.
- Come on.
- You all right, son?
You can whistle really loud,
you know that?
You know, I couldn't believe it when
the bartender told me who you are.
- And who am I, Captain Pike?
- Your father's son.
Can I get another one?
For my dissertation,
I was assigned the U.S.S. Kelvin.
Something I admired about your dad,
he didn't believe in no-win scenarios.
He sure learned his lesson.
Well, it depends
on how you define winning.
- You're here, aren't you?
- Thanks.
You know, that instinct to leap
without looking, that was his nature, too.
And in my opinion,
it's something Starfleet's lost.
- Why are you talking to me, man?
- 'Cause I looked up your file
while you were drooling on the floor.
Your aptitude tests are off the charts.
So what is it?
You like being the only genius-level
repeat-offender in the Midwest?
Maybe I love it.
So your dad dies. You can settle
for a less-than-ordinary life.
Or do you feel like you were meant
for something better?
Something special?
- Enlist in Starfleet.
- Enlist?
You guys must be way down
on your recruiting quota for the month.
If you're half the man your father was,
Jim, Starfleet could use you.
You can be an officer in four years.
You can have your own ship in eight.
You understand what the Federation is,
don't you? It's important.
It's a peacekeeping
and humanitarian armada...
- Are we done?
- I'm done.
Riverside Shipyard. Shuttle for
new recruits leaves tomorrow, 0800.
Now, your father was captain
of a starship for 12 minutes.
He saved 800 lives,
including your mother's. And yours.
I dare you to do better.
Nice ride, man.
It's yours.
Four years? I'll do it in three.
At ease, gentlemen.
- Never did get that first name.
- You need a doctor.
I told you people, I don't need a doctor,
damn it, I am a doctor!
You need to get back to your seat.
I had one in the bathroom
with no windows.
- You need to get back to your seat now.
- I suffer from aviaphobia.
It means fear of dying
in something that flies.
Sir, for your own safety, sit down,
or else I'll make you sit down!
- Fine.
- Thank you.
This is Captain Pike.
We've been cleared for takeoff.
I may throw up on you.
I think these things are pretty safe.
Don't pander to me, kid.
One tiny crack in the hull
and our blood boils in 13 seconds.
A solar flare might crop up,
cook us in our seats.
And wait till you're sitting pretty
with a case of Andorian shingles.
See if you're still so relaxed
when your eyeballs are bleeding.
Space is disease and danger
wrapped in darkness and silence.
Well, I hate to break this to you,
but Starfleet operates in space.
Yeah, well, I got nowhere else to go.
The ex-wife took the whole damn planet
in the divorce.
All I got left is my bones.
- Jim Kirk.
- McCoy. Leonard McCoy.
Captain Nero! You've been
requested on the Bridge, sir.
Ayel says it's time.
Sir, we've arrived at the coordinates
you calculated. There's nothing here.
- What are your orders?
- We wait.
We wait for the one
who allowed our home to be destroyed,
as we've been doing for 25 years.
- And once we've killed him?
- Kill him?
I'm not gonna kill him.
I'm gonna make him watch.
Capture that ship!
Welcome back, Spock.
Why are you so happy?
- I don't know what you're talking about.
- No, I don't suppose you do.
Hello, ladies!
- I'm taking the test again.
- You gotta be kidding.
Yeah, tomorrow morning,
and I want you there.
You know, I've got better things to do
than watch you embarrass yourself
for a third time.
I'm a doctor, Jim. I'm busy.
Bones, it doesn't bother you
that no one's ever passed the test?
Jim, it's the Kobayashi Maru.
No one passes the test.
And no one goes back for seconds,
let alone thirds.
I gotta study.
Study, my ass.
- Jim, I think I love you.
- That is so weird.
- Lights.
- Lights on.
Did you just say, "That is so weird"?
- Yeah, I did, but...
- You don't love me, too?
Oh, my God, my roommate!
But I thought you said
she was gone for the night.
Obviously she's not.
Quick, get under the bed.
- Under...
- Look, just get under the bed.
- Come on!
- She can't see you here.
- Why not?
- Because I promised her
- I'd stop bringing guys back to the room.
- Really?
- Well, how many guys have you...
- Just down! Just down!
- Hey.
- How are you?
- Good.
The strangest thing,
I was in the long-range sensor lab...
Yeah, I thought all night.
I was tracking solar systems and
I picked up an emergency transmission.
- Really?
- Yeah. From a Klingon prison planet.
- No.
- Yeah.
A Klingon armada was destroyed.
Forty-seven ships.
So you're not going back
to the lab tonight?
- Gaila, who is he?
- Who's who?
The mouth-breather
hiding under your bed.
You could hear me breathing?
- You!
- Big day tomorrow.
- You're gonna fail. Get out.
- Gaila, see you around.
If I pass,
will you tell me your first name?
- No! Good night.
- I think the fact
that you picked up a transmission
is very interesting.
We are receiving a distress signal
from the U.S.S. Kobayashi Maru.
The ship has lost power
and is stranded.
Starfleet Command
has ordered us to rescue them.
"Starfleet Command has ordered us
to rescue them,
"Captain."
Two Klingon vessels
have entered the Neutral Zone
- and are locking weapons on us.
- That's okay.
- That's okay?
- Yeah, don't worry about it.
Did he say, "Don't worry about it"?
Is he not taking
the simulation seriously?
Three more Klingon warbirds decloaking
and targeting our ship.
- I don't suppose this is a problem either.
- They're firing, Captain.
Alert Medical Bay to prepare to receive
all crew members
from the damaged ship.
And how do you expect us
to rescue them
when we're surrounded
by Klingons, Captain?
Alert Medical.
Our ship is being hit. Shields at 60%.
- I understand.
- Well, should we, I don't know,
fire back?
- No.
- Of course not.
What is this? What's going on?
Arm photons.
Prepare to fire on the Klingon warbirds.
- Yes, sir.
- Jim, their shields are still up.
Are they?
No. They're not.
Fire on all enemy ships.
One photon each should do.
Let's not waste ammunition.
Target locked and acquired
on all warbirds. Firing.
- All ships destroyed, Captain.
- Begin rescue of the stranded crew.
So! We've managed to eliminate
all enemy ships,
no one onboard was injured,
and the successful rescue of the
Kobayashi Maru crew is underway.
How the hell did that kid beat your test?
I do not know.
This session has been called
to resolve a troubling matter.
James T. Kirk, step forward.
Cadet Kirk, evidence has been
submitted to this council
suggesting that you violated
the ethical code of conduct
pursuant to Regulation 17.43
of the Starfleet code.
Is there anything you care to say
before we begin, sir?
Yes, I believe I have the right
to face my accuser directly.
Step forward, please.
This is Commander Spock. He is one
of our most distinguished graduates.
He's programmed the Kobayashi Maru
exam for the last four years.
- Commander?
- Cadet Kirk, you somehow managed
to install and activate a subroutine
in the programming code,
thereby changing
the conditions of the test.
- Your point being?
- In academic vernacular, you cheated.
Let me ask you something
I think we all know the answer to.
The test itself is a cheat, isn't it?
I mean, you programmed it
to be unwinnable.
Your argument precludes the possibility
of a no-win scenario.
- I don't believe in no-win scenarios.
- Then not only did you violate the rules,
you also failed to understand
the principal lesson.
Please, enlighten me.
You of all people should know,
Cadet Kirk,
a captain cannot cheat death.
I of all people?
Your father, Lieutenant George Kirk,
assumed command of his vessel
before being killed in action, did he not?
I don't think you like the fact
that I beat your test.
Furthermore, you have failed to divine
the purpose of the test.
- Enlighten me again.
- The purpose is to experience fear,
fear in the face of certain death.
To accept that fear, and maintain
control of oneself and one's crew.
This is a quality expected
in every Starfleet captain.
Excuse me, sir.
We've received a distress call
from Vulcan.
With our primary fleet engaged
in the Laurentian system,
I hereby order all cadets to report
to Hangar One immediately. Dismissed.
- Who was that pointy-eared bastard?
- I don't know, but I like him.
Fugeman, Regula One!
Gerace, U.S.S. Farragut!
McCoy, U.S.S. Enterprise!
McGrath, U.S.S. Wolcott!
Rader, U.S.S. Hood.
Welcome to Starfleet, and Godspeed.
He didn't call my name.
Commander? Sir, you didn't call
my name. Kirk, James T.
Kirk, you're on academic suspension.
That means you're grounded
until the Academy Board rules.
All right, listen up! I'm gonna read
this list one time, and one time only!
Jim, the Board will rule in your favor.
Most likely.
- Look, Jim, I gotta go.
- Yeah.
Yeah, you go. Be safe.
- Excuse me.
- Yeah. Yeah. Sure.
Damn it.
- Come with me.
- U.S.S. Newton! Uhura, U.S.S. Farragut!
Petrovsky, U.S.S. Antares!
Go to your stations and good luck.
- Bones, where are we going?
- You'll see.
- Commander, a word?
- Yes, Lieutenant?
- Was I not one of your top students?
- Indeed you were.
And did I not
on multiple occasions demonstrate
an exceptional aural sensitivity
and, I quote,
"an unparalleled ability
to identify sonic anomalies"
- in subspace transmissions tests?
- Consistently, yes.
And while you were well aware
that my unqualified desire
is to serve on the U.S.S. Enterprise,
I'm assigned to the Farragut?
It was an attempt to avoid
the appearance of favoritism.
No. I'm assigned to the Enterprise.
- Yes, I believe you are.
- Thank you.
- What are you doing?
- I'm doing you a favor.
I couldn't just leave you there,
looking all pathetic.
Take a seat. I'm gonna give you
a vaccine against viral infection
- from Melvaran mud fleas.
- What for?
- To give you the symptoms.
- What are you talking about?
You're gonna start to lose vision
in your left eye.
Yeah, I already have.
Oh, and you're gonna get
a really bad headache and a flop sweat.
- You call this a favor?
- Yeah. You owe me one.
Kirk, James T. He is not cleared
for duty aboard the Enterprise.
Medical code states the treatment
and transport of a patient is
to be determined
at the discretion of his
attending physician, which is me.
So I'm taking Mr. Kirk aboard.
Or would you like to explain
to Captain Pike
why the Enterprise warped into a crisis
without one of its senior
medical officers?
- As you were.
- As you were. Come on.
- I might throw up on you.
- Jim, you've got to look at this.
- Jim, look.
- What?
Look.
- We need to get you changed. - I
don't feel right. I feel like I'm leaking.
Hell, it's that pointy-eared bastard.
- Mr. Spock.
- Captain.
- Engineering reports ready for launch.
- Thank you.
Ladies and gentlemen, the maiden
voyage of our newest flagship
deserves more pomp and circumstance
than we can afford today.
Her christening will just have to be
our reward for a safe return. Carry on.
All decks, this is Captain Pike.
Prepare for immediate departure.
Helm, thrusters.
Moorings retracted, Captain.
Dock Control reports ready.
Thrusters fired.
Separating from spacedock.
The fleet's cleared spacedock, Captain.
All ships ready for warp.
- Set a course for Vulcan.
- Aye-aye, Captain. Course laid in.
Maximum warp. Punch it.
Lieutenant,
where is Helmsman McKenna?
He has lungworms, sir.
He couldn't report to his post.
I'm Hikaru Sulu.
- And you are a pilot, right?
- Very much so, sir.
I'm not sure what's wrong here.
- Is the parking brake on?
- No. I'll figure it out. I'm just...
Have you disengaged
the external inertial dampener?
- Ready for warp, sir.
- Let's punch it.
- Where are we?
- Medical Bay.
- This isn't worth it.
- A little suffering's good for the soul.
- Hi! How are you?
- Come here.
- My mouth is itchy. Is that normal?
- Well, those symptoms won't last long.
- I'm going to give you a mild sedative.
- I wish I didn't know you.
Don't be such an infant.
How long is it supposed to...
Unbelievable.
- Engines at maximum warp, Captain.
- Russian whiz kid, what's your name?
- Chanko? Cherpov?
- Ensign Chekov, Pavel Andreievich, sir.
Fine, Chekov, Pavel Andreievich.
Begin ship-wide mission broadcast.
Yes, sir. Happy to.
Ensign authorization code
nine-five-Wictor-Wictor-two.
Authorization not recognized.
Ensign authorization code
nine-five-Victor-Victor-two.
May I have your attention, please?
At 2200 hours, telemetry detected
an anomaly in the Neutral Zone.
What appeared to be
a lightning storm in space.
Soon after, Starfleet received a distress
signal from the Vulcan High Command
that their planet
was experiencing seismic activity.
Our mission is to assess
the condition of Vulcan
and assist in evacuations if necessary.
We should be arriving at Vulcan within
three minutes. Thank you for your time.
- Lightning storm.
- Jim, you're awake. How do you feel?
- Good God, man.
- What?
- What the hell's this?
- A reaction to the vaccine, damn it!
Nurse Chapel,
I need 50 cc's of cortisone!
Yes, sir!
... appeared to be
a lightning storm in space.
- Hey!
- We gotta stop the ship.
Jim! I'm not kidding!
We need to keep your heart rate down!
Computer, locate crew member Uhura.
You know, I haven't seen a reaction
this severe since med school.
- We're flying into a trap!
- Damn it, Jim, stand still!
Stop it!
- Uhura! Uhura...
- Kirk! What are you doing here?
The transmission from the Klingon
prison planet. What exactly...
Oh, my God,
what's wrong with your hands?
It's... Look, who is responsible
for the Klingon attack?
- What?
- And was the ship...
Was the ship what?
- What's happening to my mouth?
- You got numb tongue?
- Numb tongue?
- I can fix that.
- Was the ship what?
- Romulan.
- What? I...
- Romulan?
- Yeah!
- Yes.
- Yes?
Damn it!
Prod Nero. Seven Federation ships
are on their way.
- Jim!
- What's going on?
- Jim, come back!
- Kirk!
- Captain! Captain Pike, sir...
- Jim, come back here!
...we have to stop the ship!
- Kirk, how the hell
did you get onboard the Enterprise?
Captain, this man's under the influence
- of a severe reaction to a vaccine.
- Bones, please...
He's completely delusional,
and I take full responsibility.
Vulcan is not experiencing
a natural disaster.
It's being attacked by Romulans.
Romulans? Cadet Kirk, I think you've
had enough attention for one day.
McCoy, take him back to medical.
- We'll have words later.
- Aye, Captain.
Look, sir, that same anomaly
that we saw today...
Mr. Kirk is not cleared
to be aboard this vessel, Captain.
- I get it. You're a great arguer.
- By Regulations...
- I'd love to do it again.
...that makes him a stowaway.
- I can remove the cadet...
- Try it!
- Kirk...
- This cadet is trying to save the Bridge.
By recommending a full stop mid-warp
during a rescue mission?
It's not a rescue mission.
Listen to me, it's an attack.
Based on what facts?
That same anomaly, a lightning storm
in space that we saw today,
also occurred on the day of my birth,
before a Romulan ship
attacked the U.S.S. Kelvin.
You know that, sir,
I read your dissertation.
That ship, which had formidable
and advanced weaponry,
was never seen or heard from again.
The Kelvin attack took place
on the edge of Klingon space,
and at 2300 hours last night,
there was an attack.
Forty-seven Klingon warbirds
destroyed by Romulans, sir,
and it was reported that the Romulans
were in one ship, one massive ship.
And you know
of this Klingon attack how?
Sir, I intercepted and translated
the message myself.
- Kirk's report is accurate.
- We're warping into a trap, sir.
The Romulans are waiting for us,
I promise you that.
The cadet's logic is sound.
And Lieutenant Uhura is unmatched
in xenolinguistics.
We would be wise
to accept her conclusion.
Scan Vulcan space. Check
for any transmissions in Romulan.
Sir, I'm not sure I can distinguish
the Romulan language from Vulcan.
What about you?
Do you speak Romulan, Cadet...
Uhura. All three dialects, sir.
- Uhura, relieve the lieutenant.
- Yes, sir.
Hannity, hail the U.S.S. Truman.
All the other ships are out of warp, sir,
and have arrived at Vulcan,
but we seem to have lost all contact.
Sir, I pick up no Romulan transmission,
- or transmission of any kind in the area.
- It's because they're being attacked.
Shields up. Red alert.
Shields up. Red alert!
Arrival at Vulcan in five seconds.
Four, three, two...
- Emergency evasive!
- On it, sir.
- Damage report!
- Deflector shields are holding.
All stations! Engineer Olson, report!
Full reverse.
Come about starboard 90 degrees.
Drop us down underneath them, Sulu.
Sir, there's another Federation ship!
- Destroy it, too.
- Fire torpedoes.
Captain, they're locking torpedoes.
Divert auxiliary power from port nacelles
to forward shields.
- Sulu, status report.
- Shields at 32%.
Their weapons are powerful, sir.
We can't take another hit like that.
Get me Starfleet Command.
Captain, the Romulan ship has lowered
some kind of high-energy pulse device
into the Vulcan atmosphere.
Its signal appears to be blocking
our communications
- and transporter abilities.
- All power to forward shields.
Prepare to fire all weapons.
- Weapons ready.
- Wait!
- The hull. Magnify.
- Yes, sir.
Captain, we're being hailed.
Hello.
I'm Captain Christopher Pike.
To whom am I speaking?
Hi, Christopher. I'm Nero.
You've declared war
against the Federation.
Withdraw, I'll agree to arrange
a conference with Romulan leadership
- at a neutral location.
- I do not speak for the Empire.
We stand apart.
As does your Vulcan crew member.
Isn't that right, Spock?
Pardon me, I do not believe
that you and I are acquainted.
No, we're not. Not yet.
Spock, there's something
I would like you to see.
Captain Pike,
your transporter has been disabled.
As you can see by the rest
of your armada, you have no choice.
You will man a shuttle and come aboard
the Narada for negotiations.
That is all.
- He'll kill you. You know that.
- Your survival is unlikely.
Captain, we gain nothing by diplomacy.
Going over to that ship is a mistake.
I, too, agree.
You should rethink your strategy.
I understand that.
I need officers who've been trained
in advanced hand-to-hand combat.
- I have training, sir.
- Come with me.
Kirk, you, too.
You're not supposed to be here anyway.
- Chekov, you have the conn.
- Aye-aye, Captain.
Prepare the red matter.
Yes, sir.
Without transporters,
we can't beam off the ship,
we can't assist Vulcan,
we can't do our job.
Mr. Kirk, Mr. Sulu, Engineer Olson
will space-jump from the shuttle.
You will land on that machine
they've lowered into the atmosphere
that's scrambling our gear.
You'll get inside, you'll disable it,
then you'll beam back to the ship.
Mr. Spock, I'm leaving you
in command of the Enterprise.
Once we have transport capability
and communications back up,
you'll contact Starfleet and report
what the hell's going on here.
And if all else fails, fall back
and rendezvous with the fleet
in the Laurentian system.
Kirk, I'm promoting you to first officer.
- What?
- Captain?
Please, I apologize, the complexities
of human pranks escape me.
It's not a prank, Spock.
And I'm not the Captain, you are.
Let's go.
Sir, after we knock out that drill,
what happens to you?
Well, I guess you'll have to come
and get me.
Careful with the ship, Spock,
she's brand new.
Dr. Puri, report.
It's McCoy.
Dr. Puri was on Deck 6. He's dead.
Then you have just inherited his
responsibility as chief medical officer.
Yeah, tell me something I don't know.
Shuttle 37, you're clear forward!
Shuttle 89, U.S.S. Enterprise,
you are clear forward.
Interval check shows
positive and steady.
- You got the charges, right?
- Oh, yeah.
I can't wait to kick some Romulan ass.
Right?
- Yeah.
- Hell, yeah.
Shuttle command, we advise
you activate your shields now.
So what kind of combat training
do you have?
Fencing.
Pre-jump.
Shuttle commander, you are clear
from U.S.S. Enterprise airspace.
Gentlemen, we're approaching
the drop zone.
We have one shot
to land on that platform.
They may have defenses,
so pull your chute as late as possible.
Three, two, one.
Remember, the Enterprise
won't be able to beam you back
until you turn off that drill.
Good luck.
Away team is entering
the atmosphere, sir.
Twenty thousand meters.
Approaching the platform
at 5,800 meters.
Kirk to Enterprise.
Distance to target, 5,000 meters.
Forty-six hundred meters
from the platform.
Forty-five hundred meters to target.
Four thousand meters.
- Three thousand meters.
- Two thousand meters.
- Pulling chute.
- Two thousand meters!
- Come on, pull your chute, Olson!
No, not yet! Not yet! 1,500 meters!
- Olson, open your chute!
- Olson, pull your chute!
One thousand meters!
No!
Olson!
Olson is gone, sir!
Kirk has landed, sir.
Give me your hand! Come on.
Olson had the charges.
I know.
- What do we do?
- This.
The jamming signal's gone.
Transport abilities are reestablished.
- Transporter control is reengaged, sir.
- Chekov, run gravitational sensors.
I want to know
what they are doing to the planet.
Aye, Commander.
Captain. Sorry. Captain.
The drill's been sabotaged, sir,
but we have reached the planet's core.
Launch the red matter.
Kirk to Enterprise. They just launched
something at the planet
through the hole they just drilled.
- Do you copy, Enterprise?
- Yes, sir.
- Analyzing data now.
- Transporter is now operational.
Captain, gravitational sensors
are off the scale.
If my calculations are correct,
they're creating a singularity
that will consume the planet.
They're creating a black hole
at the center of Vulcan?
- Yes, sir.
- How long does the planet have?
Minutes, sir. Minutes.
Alert Vulcan Command Center
to signal a planet-wide evacuation,
- all channels, all frequencies.
- Spock, wait!
- Maintain standard orbit.
- Yes, sir.
- Where are you going?
- To evacuate the Vulcan High Council.
They are tasked
with protecting our cultural history.
- My parents will be among them.
- Can't you beam them out?
It is impossible.
They will be in the katric ark.
I must get them myself.
- Chekov, you have the conn.
- Aye.
- Kirk to Enterprise! Beam us out of here!
- Stand by. Locking on your signal.
- Retract the drill. Let's move out.
- Yes, sir. Pull it up!
I can't lock on to you.
Don't move. Don't move!
- Kirk!
- Sulu!
Sulu!
Hold on!
I got you! Now pull my chute!
Kirk to Enterprise! We're falling
without a chute! Beam us up!
- I'm trying. I can't lock on to your signal.
- Beam us up!
- You're moving too fast.
I can do that. I can do that!
- Take the conn!
- Aye, sir.
The black hole's expanding.
We won't reach minimum safe distance
if we don't leave immediately.
Move, move, move, move, move!
I can do that! I can do that!
Move, move, move, move!
Quick, give me manual control!
I can lock on!
Beam us up!
Enterprise, where are you?
Hold on, hold on, hold on!
Now, now, now! Do it now!
Now, now, now, now!
Okay, okay, okay! Hold on! Hold on!
Compensating gravitational pull, and...
Gotcha!
- Thanks.
- No problem.
Clear the pad.
I'm beaming to the surface.
The surface of what?
What, are you going down there?
Are you nuts?
Spock, you can't do that!
- Energize.
- Spock!
- The planet has only seconds left.
We must evacuate.
Mother, now!
- Spock to Enterprise. Get us out now.
- Locking volume.
Don't move. Stay right where you are.
Transport in five, four, three, two...
- Mother!
- I'm losing her!
I'm losing her! I'm losing her!
No! I lost her. I lost her.
Acting Captain's Log, Stardate 2258.42.
We have had no word
from Captain Pike.
I have therefore classified him
a hostage of the war criminal
known as Nero.
Nero, who has destroyed
my home planet
and most of its six billion inhabitants.
While the essence of our culture
has been saved
in the elders
who now reside upon this ship,
I estimate no more than 10,000
have survived.
I am now a member
of an endangered species.
I'm sorry.
I'm so sorry.
What do you need? Tell me.
Tell me.
I need everyone
to continue performing admirably.
Okay.
You must have
a lot of questions for me.
I only have one for you.
I need the subspace frequencies
of Starfleet's border protection grids,
specifically those surrounding Earth.
Christopher, answer my question.
No, you answer for the genocide
you just committed
- against a peaceful planet.
- No, I prevented genocide.
In my time, where I come from,
this is a simple mining vessel.
I chose a life of honest labor
to provide for myself and the wife
who was expecting my child.
I was off planet, doing my job
while your Federation did nothing
and allowed my people to burn
while their planet broke in half.
And Spock, he didn't help us.
He betrayed us!
No, you're confused.
You've been misinformed.
Romulus hasn't been destroyed.
It's out there right now.
You're blaming the Federation
for something that hasn't happened.
It has happened! I watched it happen!
I saw it happen!
Don't tell me it didn't happen!
And when I lost her,
I promised myself retribution.
And for 25 years I planned my revenge
against the Federation,
and forgot what it was like
to live a normal life.
But I did not forget the pain.
It's a pain that every surviving Vulcan
now shares.
My purpose, Christopher,
is to not simply avoid
the destruction of the home that I love,
but to create a Romulus
that exists free of the Federation.
You see, only then
will she be truly saved.
That is why I will destroy
all the remaining Federation planets,
starting with yours.
Then we have nothing left to discuss.
You will give me the frequencies
to disable Earth's defenses.
Centaurian slugs.
They latch on to your brain stem
and release a toxin
that will force you to answer.
Frequencies, please, sir.
Christopher Pike,
Captain, U.S.S. Enterprise...
As you wish.
Have you confirmed
that Nero is headed for Earth?
Their trajectory suggests
no other destination, Captain.
- Thank you, Lieutenant.
- Earth may be his next stop,
but we have to assume
every Federation planet's a target.
Out of the chair.
Well, if the Federation is a target,
why didn't they destroy us?
Why would they? Why waste a weapon?
We obviously weren't a threat.
That is not it.
He said he wanted me
to see something,
the destruction of my home planet.
How the hell did they do that,
by the way?
I mean, where did the Romulans
get that kind of weaponry?
The engineering comprehension
necessary
to artificially create a black hole
may suggest an answer.
Such technology
could theoretically be manipulated
to create a tunnel through space-time.
Damn it, man,
I'm a doctor, not a physicist.
Are you actually suggesting
they're from the future?
If you eliminate the impossible,
whatever remains, however improbable,
- must be the truth.
- How poetic.
Then what would an angry
future Romulan want with Captain Pike?
As Captain, he does know details
of Starfleet's defenses.
What we need to do
is catch up to that ship,
disable it, take it over and get Pike back.
We are technologically outmatched
in every way.
A rescue attempt would be illogical.
Nero's ship would have to drop
out of warp for us to overtake them.
Then what about
assigning engineering crews
- to try and boost our warp yield?
- Remaining crew are repairing
- radiation leaks on the lower decks...
- Okay! All right!
...and damage to subspace
communications, without which
- we cannot contact Starfleet.
- There's got to be some way...
We must gather
with the rest of Starfleet
to balance the terms
of the next engagement.
There won't be a next engagement.
By the time we've gathered,
it'll be too late.
But you say he's from the future,
knows what's gonna happen?
Then the logical thing
is to be unpredictable.
You're assuming that Nero knows
how events are predicted to unfold.
The contrary, Nero's very presence
has altered the flow of history,
beginning with the attack
on the U.S.S. Kelvin,
culminating in the events of today,
thereby creating
an entire new chain of incidents
that cannot be anticipated
by either party.
An alternate reality.
Precisely.
Whatever our lives might have been,
if the time continuum was disrupted,
our destinies have changed.
Mr. Sulu, plot a course for the
Laurentian system, warp factor 3.
Spock, don't do that.
Running back to the rest of the fleet
for a confab is a massive waste of time.
These are the orders issued
by Captain Pike when he left the ship.
He also ordered us
to go back and get him.
Spock, you are Captain now.
You have to make...
I am aware of my responsibilities,
Mr. Kirk.
Every second we waste, Nero's
getting closer to his next target.
That is correct, and why
I'm instructing you to accept the fact
- that I alone am in command.
- I will not allow us to go backwards...
- Jim, he's the Captain!
...away from the problem,
- instead of hunting Nero down!
- Security, escort him out.
- Hey!
- Enough, Jim!
Get him off this ship.
- Computer, where am I?
- Location, Delta Vega.
Class-M planet. Unsafe.
There is a Starfleet outpost
14 kilometers to the northwest.
Remain in your pod
- until retrieved by Starfleet authorities.
- You gotta be kidding me.
Stardate 2258.42.
Or 44. Whatever.
Acting Captain Spock
has marooned me on Delta Vega,
in what I believe to be
a violation of Security Protocol 49.09
governing the treatment of prisoners
aboard a star...
James T. Kirk.
- Excuse me?
- How did you find me?
How do you know my name?
I have been and always shall be
your friend.
- Look, I don't know you.
- I am Spock.
Bullshit.
It is remarkably pleasing
to see you again, old friend.
Especially after the events of today.
Sir, I appreciate
what you did for me today,
but if you were Spock,
you'd know we're not friends. At all.
You hate me.
You marooned me here for mutiny.
- Mutiny?
- Yes.
You are not the captain?
No, no, you're the captain.
Pike was taken hostage.
By Nero.
What do you know about him?
He is a particularly troubled Romulan.
- Please, allow me. It will be easier.
- What are you doing?
Our minds, one and together.
One hundred twenty-nine years
from now,
a star will explode
and threaten to destroy the galaxy.
That is where I'm from, Jim, the future.
A star went supernova,
consuming everything in its path.
I promised the Romulans
that I would save their planet.
We outfitted our fastest ship.
Using red matter,
I would create a black hole
which would absorb the exploding star.
I was en route,
when the unthinkable happened.
The supernova destroyed Romulus.
I had little time.
I had to extract the red matter
and shoot it into the supernova.
As I began my return trip,
I was intercepted.
He called himself Nero,
last of the Romulan Empire.
In my attempt to escape, both of us
were pulled into the black hole.
Nero went through first.
He was the first to arrive.
Nero and his crew spent
the next 25 years awaiting my arrival.
But what was years for Nero
was only seconds for me.
I went through the black hole.
Nero was waiting for me.
He held me responsible
for the loss of his world.
He captured my vessel
and spared my life,
for one reason.
So that I would know his pain.
He beamed me here
so that I could observe his vengeance.
As he was helpless to save his planet,
I would be helpless to save mine.
Billions of lives lost because of me, Jim.
Because I failed.
Forgive me. Emotional transference
is an effect of the mind-meld.
- So you do feel.
- Yes.
Going back in time,
you changed all our lives.
Jim, we must go.
There is a Starfleet outpost
not far from here.
Wait. Where you came from,
did I know my father?
Yes.
You often spoke of him as being
your inspiration for joining Starfleet.
He proudly lived to see you
become Captain of the Enterprise.
Captain?
A ship we must return you to
as soon as possible.
- Warp 3, sir.
- Course 1-5-1, mark 3.
- Laurentian system, sir.
- Thank you, gentlemen.
- You wanted to see me?
- Yes, Doctor.
I am aware that James Kirk is
a friend of yours.
I recognize that supporting me
as you did must have been difficult.
Is that a thank-you?
I am simply acknowledging
your difficulties.
Permission to speak freely, sir.
- I welcome it.
- Do you? Okay, then.
Are you out of your Vulcan mind?
Are you making a logical choice,
sending Kirk away?
Probably. But the right one?
You know, back home we got a saying,
"If you're gonna ride
in the Kentucky Derby,
"you don't leave your prize stallion
in the stable."
A curious metaphor, Doctor,
as a stallion must first be broken
before it can reach its potential.
My God, man, you could at least act
like it was a hard decision!
I intend to assist in the effort
to reestablish communication
with Starfleet.
However, if crew morale is better served
by my roaming the halls weeping,
I will gladly defer
to your medical expertise.
Excuse me.
Green-blooded hobgoblin.
Hello!
What?
You realize how unacceptable this is?
- Fascinating.
- What?
Okay, I'm sure you're just
doing your job,
but could you not have come
a wee bit sooner?
Six months I've been here,
living off Starfleet protein nibs
and the promise of a good meal!
And I know exactly
what's going on here, okay?
Punishment, isn't it? Ongoing.
For something
that was clearly an accident.
- You are Montgomery Scott.
- You know him?
Aye, that's me. You're in the right place.
Unless there's another hardworking,
equally starved Starfleet officer around.
- Me.
- Get aff! Shut up!
You don't eat anything!
You can eat, like, a bean,
and you're done.
I'm talking about food. Real food.
But you're here now, so thank you.
Where is it?
You are, in fact, the Mr. Scott
who postulated
the theory of transwarp beaming.
That's what I'm talking about.
How do you think I wound up here?
I had a little debate with my instructor
on the issue of relativistic physics
and how it pertains to subspace travel.
He seemed to think that the range of
transporting something like a grapefruit
was limited to about 100 miles.
I told him that I could not only
beam a grapefruit from one planet
to the adjacent planet
in the same system,
which is easy, by the way,
I could do it with a life-form.
So, I tested it on Admiral Archer's
prize beagle.
- I know that dog. What happened to it?
- I'll tell you when it reappears.
I don't know. I do feel guilty about that.
What if I told you
that your transwarp theory was correct,
that it is indeed possible to beam onto
a ship that is traveling at warp speed?
I think if that equation had been
discovered, I'd have heard about it.
The reason you haven't heard of it,
Mr. Scott,
is because you haven't discovered it yet.
- Are you from the future?
- Yeah, he is. I'm not.
Well, that's brilliant.
Do they still have sandwiches there?
Well, she's a wee bit dodgy.
Shield emitters are totally banjaxed,
as well as a few other things.
On youse go.
So the Enterprise has had
its maiden voyage, has it?
She is one well-endowed lady.
I'd like to get my hands
on her ample nacelles,
if you'll pardon
the engineering parlance.
Except, the thing is,
even if I believed you, right,
where you're from, what I've done,
which I don't, by the way,
you're still talking about
beaming aboard the Enterprise
while she's traveling faster than light
without a proper receiving pad.
Get off there! It's not a climbing frame.
The notion of transwarp beaming is like
trying to hit a bullet with a smaller bullet
whilst wearing a blindfold,
riding a horse.
What's that?
Your equation
for achieving transwarp beaming.
Get out of it.
Imagine that!
It never occurred to me to think of space
as the thing that was moving.
You're coming with us, right?
- No, Jim. That is not my destiny.
- Your...
He... The other Spock
is not gonna believe me.
Only you can explain
what the hell's happened.
Under no circumstances
can he be made aware of my existence.
You must promise me this.
You're telling me I can't tell you
that I'm following your own orders?
- Why not? What happens?
- Jim, this is one rule you cannot break.
To stop Nero, you alone
must take command of your ship.
- How? Over your dead body?
- Preferably not.
However, there is
Starfleet Regulation 619.
Six-one-nine states
that any command officer
who's emotionally compromised
by the mission at hand
must resign said command.
So, you're saying that I have
to emotionally compromise you guys.
Jim, I just lost my planet.
I can tell you,
I am emotionally compromised.
What you must do is get me to show it.
Aye, then, laddie.
Live or die. Let's get this over with.
No, go. You cannae come with me.
Go on.
You know, coming back in time,
changing history,
that's cheating.
A trick I learned from an old friend.
Live long and prosper.
Mr. Scott!
Mr. Scott, can you hear me?
Hold on a second!
Oh, no.
Don't worry, I...
No. No!
Turbine release valve activated.
You all right? You all right?
My head's buzzing and I'm soaked,
but otherwise I'm fine.
Captain Spock! Detecting unauthorized
access to Water Turbine Control Board.
Bring up the video.
Security, seal the Engineering Deck.
We have intruders in Turbine Section 3.
Set phasers to stun.
- Halt!
- No, no!
Come with me, cupcake!
- Who are you?
- I'm with him.
- He's with me.
- We are traveling at warp speed.
How did you manage
to beam aboard this ship?
Well, you're the genius,
you figure it out.
As acting captain of this vessel,
I order you to answer the question.
Well, I'm not telling, Acting Captain.
What, did...
That doesn't frustrate you, does it?
My lack of cooperation?
- That doesn't make you angry.
- Are you a member of Starfleet?
I... Yes. Can I get a towel, please?
Under penalty of court martial,
I order you to explain to me
how you were able to beam
aboard this ship while moving at warp.
- Well...
- Don't answer him.
You will answer me.
- I'd rather not take sides.
- What is it with you, Spock?
Your planet was just destroyed,
your mother murdered,
- and you're not even upset.
- Lf you are presuming
that these experiences in any way
impede my ability to command this ship,
- you are mistaken.
- And yet, you are the one
who said fear was necessary
for command.
I mean, did you see his ship?
Did you see what he did?
- Yes, of course I did.
- So are you afraid or aren't you?
I will not allow you to lecture me
about the merits of emotion.
- Then why don't you stop me?
- Step away from me, Mr. Kirk.
What is it like not to feel anger?
Or heartbreak?
Or the need to stop at nothing
to avenge the death
of the woman who gave birth to you?
- Back away from me.
- You feel nothing!
It must not even compute for you.
You never loved her!
Spock!
Doctor, I am no longer fit for duty.
I hereby relinquish my command,
based on the fact that I have been
emotionally compromised.
Please note the time and date
in the ship's log.
I like this ship! You know, it's exciting!
Well, congratulations, Jim.
Now we've got no captain, and
no goddamn first officer to replace him.
Yeah, we do.
- What?
- Pike made him first officer.
- You gotta be kidding me.
- Thanks for the support.
I sure hope you know
what you're doing, Captain.
So do I.
Attention, crew of the Enterprise.
This is James Kirk.
Mr. Spock has resigned commission
and advanced me to acting captain.
I know you were all expecting
to regroup with the fleet,
but I'm ordering a pursuit course
of the enemy ship to Earth.
I want all departments at battle stations
and ready in 10 minutes.
Either we're going down or they are.
Kirk out.
Speak your mind, Spock.
That would be unwise.
What is necessary is never unwise.
I am as conflicted
as I once was as a child.
You will always be a child of two worlds.
I am grateful for this.
And for you.
I feel anger
for the one who took Mother's life.
An anger I cannot control.
I believe that she would say,
"Do not try to."
You asked me once
why I married your mother.
I married her because I loved her.
Whatever the case, we need
to get aboard Nero's ship undetected.
We can't just go in there guns blazing,
Jim, not with their technology.
I'm telling you, the math doesn't support
what you're suggesting.
- Captain Kirk. Captain Kirk!
- Yes, Mr. Chekov. What is it?
Based on the Narada's course
from Vulcan,
I have projected that Nero
will travel past Saturn.
Like you said, we need to stay invisible
to Nero or he'll destroy us.
If Mr. Scott can get us to warp factor 4,
and if we drop out of warp behind
one of Saturn's moons, say, Titan,
the magnetic distortion
from the planet's rings
will make us invisible to Nero's sensors.
From there,
as long as the drill is not actuated,
- we can beam aboard the enemy ship.
- Aye, that might work.
Wait a minute, kid. How old are you?
- Seventeen, sir.
- Oh, good, he's 17.
Doctor.
Mr. Chekov is correct.
I can confirm his telemetry.
If Mr. Sulu is able
to maneuver us into position,
I can beam aboard Nero's ship,
steal back the black hole device
and, if possible,
bring back Captain Pike.
I won't allow you to do that, Mr. Spock.
Romulans and Vulcans
share a common ancestry.
Our cultural similarities
will make it easier for me
to access the ship's computer
to locate the device.
Also, my mother was human,
which makes Earth
the only home I have left.
Then I'm coming with you.
I would cite Regulation,
but I know you will simply ignore it.
See? We are
getting to know each other.
Prepare the drill.
All stop in three, two, one.
Give me one-quarter impulse burst
for five seconds.
I'll do the rest with thrusters.
On my mark.
- Aye.
- Fire.
Transporter Room.
We are in position above Titan.
Really? Fine job, Mr. Sulu. Well done.
- How are we, Scotty?
- Unbelievably, sir, the ship is in position.
Whatever happens, Mr. Sulu,
if you think you have
the tactical advantage,
you fire on that ship, even if we're still
onboard. That's an order.
Yes, sir.
Otherwise we'll contact the Enterprise
when we're ready to be beamed back.
Good luck.
- I will be back.
- You better be.
- I'll be monitoring your frequency.
- Thank you, Nyota.
- So her first name's Nyota?
- I have no comment on the matter.
Okey-dokey, then,
if there's any common sense
in the design of the enemy ship,
I should be putting you
somewhere in the Cargo Bay.
- Shouldn't be a soul in sight.
- Energize.
Captain, we have Starfleet officers
aboard the ship.
- One of them is Vulcan.
- No.
Ayel!
I'll cover you.
- Are you certain?
- Yeah, I got you.
Do you know where it is?
The black hole device.
And Captain Pike.
Move!
They have activated the drill.
Communication and transport
are inoperative.
Sulu, please tell me you have them.
Otherwise we won't be able
to beam them back.
Kirk and Spock are on their own now.
I foresee a complication.
The design of their ship is far
more advanced than I had anticipated.
Voice print and face recognition
analysis enabled.
Welcome back, Ambassador Spock.
Wow, that's weird.
Computer, what is
your manufacturing origin?
Stardate 2387. Commissioned
by the Vulcan Science Academy.
It appears that you have been keeping
important information from me.
You're gonna be able
to fly this thing, right?
Something tells me I already have.
- Good luck.
- Jim.
The statistical likelihood that our plan
will succeed is less than 4.3%.
- It'll work.
- In the event that I do not return,
- please tell Lieutenant Uhura...
- Spock!
Lt'll work.
Fascinating.
Start-up sequence initiated.
Nero, order your men to disable the drill
or I will...
I know your face from Earth's history.
James T. Kirk was considered
to be a great man.
He went on to captain
the U.S.S. Enterprise.
But that was another life.
A life I will deprive you of,
just like I did your father.
Captain Nero. The Vulcan ship has been
taken. The drill has been destroyed.
Spock!
- Open a channel.
- Yes, sir!
Spock. I knew I should have killed you
when I had the chance.
I hereby confiscate
this illegally obtained ship
and order you to surrender your vessel.
- No terms. No deals.
- That ship, take it out.
Sir, if you ignite the red matter,
- you'll destroy...
- I want Spock dead now!
- He went to warp, sir.
- Go after him!
Yes, sir!
Your species is even weaker
than I expected.
- I can't...
- You can't what?
You can't even speak.
- What?
- I got your gun.
What's he doing?
Ambassador Spock,
you are on a collision course.
Fire everything!
Incoming missiles. If the ship is hit,
the red matter will be ignited.
Understood.
Captain, I've picked up another ship!
- What are you doing here?
- Just following orders.
Enterprise, now!
Nice timing, Scotty!
I've never beamed three people
from two targets onto one pad before!
- Jim!
- Bones!
I got him.
That was pretty good!
Captain, the enemy ship is losing
power! Their shields are down, sir.
- Hail them now.
- Aye.
This is Captain James T. Kirk
of the U.S.S. Enterprise.
Your ship is compromised.
Too close to the singularity
to survive without assistance,
which we are willing to provide.
- Captain, what are you doing?
- Showing them compassion
may be the only way
to earn peace with Romulus.
It's logic, Spock.
I thought you'd like that.
No, not really. Not this time.
I would rather suffer the end of Romulus
a thousand times.
I would rather die in agony
than accept assistance from you.
You got it.
- Arm phasers. Fire everything we've got.
- Yes, sir.
- Sulu, let's go home.
- Yes, sir!
- Why aren't we at warp?
- We are, sir.
Kirk to Engineering.
Get us out of here, Scotty.
You bet your ass, Captain!
Captain, we're caught in the gravity well!
It's got us!
- Go to maximum warp! Push it!
- I'm giving her all she's got, Captain!
All she's got isn't good enough!
- What else you got?
- Okay, if we eject the core and detonate,
the blast could be enough
to push us away.
I cannae promise anything, though!
Do it, do it, do it!
- Clear the area! Go!
- Yes, sir!
Father!
I am not our father.
There are so few Vulcans left.
We cannot afford to ignore each other.
Then why did you send Kirk aboard
when you alone
could have explained the truth?
Because you needed each other.
I could not deprive you
of the revelation of all
that you could accomplish together,
of a friendship that will define you both
in ways you cannot yet realize.
How did you persuade him
to keep your secret?
He inferred that universe-ending
paradoxes would ensue
- should he break his promise.
- You lied.
I... I implied.
- A gamble.
- An act of faith.
One I hope that you'll repeat
in the future in Starfleet.
In the face of extinction, it is only logical
I resign my Starfleet commission
and help rebuild our race.
And yet,
you can be in two places at once.
I urge you to remain in Starfleet.
I have already located a suitable planet
on which to establish a Vulcan colony.
Spock, in this case, do yourself a favor.
Put aside logic. Do what feels right.
Since my customary farewell
would appear oddly self-serving,
I shall simply say
good luck.
This assembly calls Captain
James Tiberius Kirk.
Your inspirational valor and
supreme dedication to your comrades
is in keeping with
the highest traditions of service,
and reflect utmost credit to yourself,
your crew and the Federation.
It is my honor to award you
with this commendation.
By Starfleet Order 28455,
you are hereby directed to report
to Admiral Pike, U.S.S. Enterprise,
for duty as his relief.
I relieve you, sir.
I am relieved.
- Thank you, sir.
- Congratulations, Captain.
Your father would be proud.
Thrusters on full.
Maneuvering thrusters and
impulse engines at your command, sir.
Weapons systems and shields
on standby.
Dock Control reports ready, Captain.
Bones! Buckle up.
Scotty, how we doing?
Dilithium chamber's
at maximum, Captain.
Get down!
Mr. Sulu, prepare to engage thrusters.
Permission to come aboard, Captain.
Permission granted.
As you have yet to select a first officer,
respectfully I would like to submit
my candidacy.
Should you desire,
I can provide character references.
It would be my honor, Commander.
Maneuvering thrusters, Mr. Sulu.
Thrusters on standby.
- Take us out.
- Aye-aye, Captain.
Space, the final frontier.
These are the voyages
of the Starship Enterprise.
Her ongoing mission,
to explore strange new worlds,
to seek out new life-forms
and new civilizations,
to boldly go
where no one has gone before.